{"tossups": [{"question": "This colony suffered the Plundering Time, which ended shortly before William Stone was appointed governor. The so-called \u201clast battle of the English Civil War\u201d took place in this colony as Captain William Fuller successfully led Commonwealth troops in the Battle of the Severn. This colony, settled by pilgrims aboard the<em> Ark</em> and<em> Dove</em>, passed a 1649 Toleration Act, despite the Catholic faith of its founders. For ten points, name this colony founded by Cecil Calvert, who had the title of Lord Baltimore.", "answer": "Province of<b> Maryland</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A monument in this city, decorated with carvings of azaelas, is found at the foot of Moran Hill and is modeled after the Arc de Triomphe. One building in this city, shaped like a pyramid with three wings, first topped out at 105 floors in 1992 but has yet to open to the public. A flame-topped monument in this city is named after the state ideology. The Ryugyong Hotel is found in, for ten points, what city also home to the Arch of Reunification, the Juche Tower, and Kim Il-Sung Square?", "answer": "<b> Pyongyang</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "At one trial for this crime, Governor Ross Barnett shook hands with the defendant in pointed view of the jury. Five days before this event, its target was nearly run down by a car; a week before that, a Molotov cocktail was thrown at his house. After two all-white juries were deadlocked, the perpetrator of this event was finally prosecuted for it in 1994, with his boasting at KKK rallies about shooting the\u201cuppity\u201d victim in the back used as evidence against him. For ten points, name this June 12, 1963 event in which Byron de la Beckwith shot the NAACP\u2019s field secretary for Mississippi.", "answer": "the<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>, etc.) of Medgar<b> Evers</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A character in this novel receives a book of<em> Great Peace</em> from the spirit of an old man with a walking stick. In this book, two friends are turned against each other after a south wind fails to materialize, and one of those men constructs the Stone Sentinel Maze in battle. Three men in this novel agree to becomes brothers when they swear an oath in a peach garden. This book\u2019s climactic scene is the Battle of Red Cliffs. For ten points, name this historical Chinese novel partially named after the states of Wei, Wu, and Shu.", "answer": "The<b> Romance of the Three Kingdoms</b> (or<b> San Guo Yan Yi</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "With its northern neighbor, this region produces a red pudding named rodgrod. A historic port in this region is home to salt warehouses known as Salzspeicher. The November Constitution attempted to create a joint parliament with this region, bypassing the London Protocol of 1852. A conflict over this region was ended by the Gastein Convention. A group of islands belonging to this present-day region, Heligoland, was swapped with Zanzibar in an 1890 treaty. This region, home to the Hanseatic city of L\u00a8ubeck, is crossed by the Kiel Canal. For ten points, name this northern German region once contested with Denmark.", "answer": "<b> Schleswig-Holstein</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One of these specific objects named the<em> Michael</em> is on display at a museum in Bovington. The Lima Locomotive Works was the first factory to produce these objects. A modified type of this vehicle known as a \u201cCrab\u201d was used by \u201cHobart\u2019s Funnies.\u201d Close to 80 percent of these vehicles, which were lighter than a similar vehicle named for Churchill, were provided by the Lend-Lease program. These vehicles carried a 75-milimeter gun, used in frequent clashes with German Panzers. For ten points, name this medium-sized American tank, named after a Civil War general who led the March to the Sea.", "answer": "M4<b> Sherman</b> Tank (accept Medium Tank,<b> M4</b>; prompt on tank before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of these pieces, the fifth by its composer, includes an \u201calla bulgarese\u201d scherzo possibly inspired by its composer\u2019s ethnomusicological studies. One of these pieces also includes tape recordings of Holocaust survivors; that piece is Steve Reich\u2019s<em> Different Trains</em>. A set of variations on the<em> Deutschlandlied</em> was included in a collection of these works dedicated to Count Erdody. Bela Bartok wrote six of, for ten points, what chamber works whose \u201cfather\u201d was Joseph Haydn, consisting of two violins, a viola, and a cello?", "answer": "<b> string quartet</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "As head of the Commission on International Development Issues, this man claimed that latitude 30 degrees north demarcated rich and poor countries in his namesake report. He rejected the Hallstein Doctrine by signing the Basic Treaty with a neighboring country. This man was forced to retire after his aide, Gunter Guillaume, was discovered to be a Stasi spy. For ten points, name this socialist chancellor of West Germany who favored rapprochement with the East in his policy of<em> ostpolitik</em>.", "answer": "Willy<b> Brandt</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This scientist worked with JoBea Holt as the leader of an interactive program for children called ISS EarthKAM. This astronaut, who died of pancreatic cancer in 2012, served as CAPCOM on the ground for NASA\u2019s STS-2 and STS-3 missions before serving as a mission specialist on STS-7; prior to that mission, press members asked this figure questions like \u201cDo you weep when things go wrong?\u201d For ten points, name this first American woman in space.", "answer": "Sally Kristen<b> Ride</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. A Gib Crockett cartoon inspired by this event is titled \u201cIf Damocles Survived I Guess I Can Too.\u201d This event was carried out by an object called \u201cBear A.\u201d This event, which surpassed the effect of Castle Bravo, occurred on Severny Island and produced an energy yield one fourth the size of the eruption of Krakatoa. For ten points, name this event, alternatively known as Kuzma\u2019s mother, a Khrushchev-era hydrogen bomb test that was the most powerful man-made explosion in history.", "answer": "explosion of<b> Tsar Bomba</b> (accept<b> Ivan</b>; accept<b> Vanya</b>; accept<b> Tsar Bomb</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In a November 2016 interview, this man stated \u201cDick Cheney. Darth Vader. Satan. That\u2019s power.\u201dDuring this man\u2019s divorce proceedings, his ex-wife Mary Louis Piccard said he did not want to send his children to the Archer School for Girls because \u201cthere were too many Jews there.\u201d On January 28, this man was controversially added to the Principals Committee for the National Security Council, and he served as Trump\u2019s Campaign CEO from August to November 2016. For ten points, name this White House Chief Strategist, a former executive of the ultra-Conservative site Breitbart.", "answer": "Steve<b> Bannon</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This man married the niece of Benjamin Wade, who he defeated to attain his highest post. In that post, this man came under fire after his name appeared in Oakes Ames\u2019 list of men who owned stock in a company that underwrote the Union Pacific Railroad. For ten points, name this politician who was implicated in the Cr\u00b4edit Mobilier scandal while serving as Ulysses Grant\u2019s vice president.", "answer": "Schuyler<b> Colfax</b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In this country, Mohammed Morgan issued the \u201cLetter of Death\u201d before carrying out a genocide of the Isaaq peoples. A leader of this country created new settlements in the Jubba region to deal with the\u201cLingering Drought\u201d and was victorious at Jijiga against another country\u2019s Derg regime. In this country, foreign troops were trapped near the Baakara Market during Operation Gothic Serpent while attempting to capture a successor of Siad Barre, Mohammad Farah Aidid. For ten points, name this African country, the site of the infamous 1993 \u201cBlack Hawk Down\u201d battle in Mogadishu.", "answer": "<b> Somalia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In his autobiography<em> The Education of a Public Man</em>, this man explains the emotional importance he placed on passing the bill he initiated that called for the creation of the Peace Corps. This man worked with Elmer Kelm and Elmer Benson on the merger of two parties in his state. The McGovern-Fraser Commission was created in the aftermath of a convention that nominated this man while police used tear gas against a crowd that chanted \u201cThe whole world is watching.\u201d For ten points, name this Minnesota politician, the 1968 presidential nominee for the Democratic Party.", "answer": "Hubert Horatio<b> Humphrey</b>, Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The concept of<em> aufheben</em> in this philosopher\u2019s work is often translated as either \u201cto lift up\u201d or \u201cto abolish.\u201d The idea that consciousness can best be understood through a \u201cpure looking at\u201d comes from the famously dense preface of this man\u2019s most famous work, which was completed while this man was observing Napoleon\u2019s victory at the Battle of Jena. In that work, this man describes his concept of the dialectic as a method for reaching the truth. For ten points, name this German Idealist philosopher who wrote<em> The Phenomenology of Spirit</em>.", "answer": "Georg Wilhelm Friedrich<b> Hegel</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A</b><em><b> Punch</b></em><b> cartoon shows an organ grinder with the name of this location being shooed away from John Bull\u2019s house. An expedition bound for this location dismantled the steamer</b> <em><b>Faidherbe</b></em><b> and dragged its boiler through miles of (+)</b> <b>jungles and deserts. Christian de</b> <b>jungles and deserts. Christian de</b> <b>Bonchamps aborted his expedition to this location, where Jean-Baptiste (*)</b> <b>Bonchamps aborted his expedition to this location, where Jean-Baptiste (*)</b> Marchand and Herbert Kitchener peacefully agreed to let their foreign ministers settle a boundary dispute near the White Nile. For ten points, name this site of an 1898 incident between the British and the French in Africa.", "answer": "<b> Fashoda</b> (accept<b> Fashoda</b> Incident, Crisis, etc.; prompt on Sudan after \u201csteamer\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This scientist converted to Catholicism on his deathbed at Walter Reed, where he was kept to make sure he didn\u2019t reveal military secrets. Humorous acronyms of his include MAD, for his theory of Mutually Assured Destruction, and MANIAC, the name of a computer he</b> <b>built at (+)</b> <b>Los Alamos. This man introduced the density matrix formalism of quantum</b> <b>mechanics, and his proof of the minimax theorem inspired the field of game theory. This inventor of (*)</b> merge sort names a design in which RAM is used to store both data and instructions. For ten points, name this Hungarian-American mathematician who lends his name to a widely used computer architecture.", "answer": "John<b> von Neumann</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Computer Science"}, {"question": "\u201cWahoo\u201d and \u201cUmbrella\u201d were underwater examples of, for ten points, what military and scientific actions performed by the US at Bikini Atoll?", "answer": "US<b> nuclear</b> weapon<b> test</b>s (accept anything related to<b> test</b>s of<b> atomic bomb</b>s,<b> hydrogen bomb</b>s,<b> thermonuclear bomb</b>s, etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This ruler denounced the South African police as \u201cGestapo\u201d when prime minister Jan Smuts only allowed him to shake hands with whites. This leader\u2019s most famous oration</b> <b>denounced the \u201cprimitive doctrine that might is right\u201d on the onset of a (+)</b> <b>\u201cgrave hour</b> <b>[...] the most fateful in our history.\u201d Sovereignty was granted to this king\u2019s domains following the passage of the Statute of Westminster. This king, who worked with (*)</b> speech therapist Lionel Logue, took the throne after the abdication of his brother Edward VIII. For ten points, name this British king who led the country through World War II.", "answer": "<b> George VI</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Jonathan Pitney is known as the \u201cfather\u201d of this city, which was ruled for several decades by the policial boss Nucky Johnson. Meyer Lansky\u2019s honeymoon was used as pretext for a</b> <b>1929 conference in this city that brought together heads of (+)</b> <b>Mafia families from across</b> <b>the country. The 1964 Democratic National Convention was held in this city, where in 1870 a landmark was opened that now runs from from Absecon Inlet to neighboring (*)</b> Ventnor City. A 1976 referendum legalized casino gambling here. America\u2019s first boardwalk is found in, for ten points, what New Jersey resort town home to the Miss America pageant?", "answer": "<b> Atlantic City</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. This military operation was preceded by a series of intimidating troop movements in Operation Sand Flea. During this event, the capture of Fort Amador allowed for further action against the El Chorrillo neighborhood, which was defended by the (+) Dignity Battalions. Guillermo Endara rose to power as a result of this event, whose target was psychologically forced out of the (*) </b> Vatican embassy by loud music. Operation Just Cause was the codename of, for ten points, what military action, ordered by President George H.W. Bush, in which American troops deposed Manuel Noriega?", "answer": "1989-1990 American invasion of<b> Panama</b> (accept equivalent descriptions that mention <b>Panama</b>; accept Operation<b> Just Cause</b> before mentioned; accept descriptions of the fall of Manuel <b>Noriega</b> before his name is mentioned) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>This city was the site of a military borough known as the Albertstadt. Richard</b> <b>Wagner spent his early career in this city before fleeing in the wake of the 1848 May</b> <b>Uprisings against Frederick (+) Augustus II, the elector who ruled this city\u2019s region.</b> <b>In the 20th century, Arthur Harris was heavily criticized for authorizing an (*)</b> RAF strike on this city that killed 25,000 people in a firestorm, even though the war was nearly won. For ten points, name this capital of Saxony which was targeted in a controversial 1945 firebombing. ANSWER:<b> Dresden</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}